准备好了吗  孩子们
Are you ready, kids?
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
我听不见
I can't hear you
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
是谁住在深海的大菠萝里
Who lives in a pineapple under the sea?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
方方黄黄伸缩自如
Absorbent and yellow and porous is he
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
如果四处探险是你的愿望
If nautical nonsense be something you wish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
那就敲敲甲板让大鱼开路
Then drop on the deck and flop like a fish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
准备
Ready
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
压力
分镜总监
分镜
翻译: 1440kHz
编剧
动画总监
创意总监
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
要知道  海绵宝宝
You know, SpongeBob
有时候就应该放着滑翔翼不用
sometimes it's nice to hang up my hang glider
静静观赏云朵飘过
and just watch the clouds roll by
对
Yep
还要放松
And just relax
没错
Yeah
放松
relax
你知道那朵云像什么吗
You know what that cloud looks like?
什么
What?
一朵花
A flower
这里所有云都很像花  海绵宝宝
They all look like flowers, SpongeBob
从来都是
all the time
确实是
They sure do
平常我都会跟你比赛
You know, normally I'd offer to race you
跑到珊瑚崖上
to the top of Coral Cliffs
不过这美景我一秒都不愿意错过
but I don't want to
miss out on a second of this beautiful beauty
我也是
Me either
谁还会想一起比一比
Who wants to get all dirty anyway?
对啊
Yeah
那样还会流汗
and sweaty
并且咱俩心知肚明谁会先登顶
Besides, I think we know who'd get to the top first
对
Yeah
我
Me
真好笑  珊迪
That's funny, Sandy
你刚好像说
It sounded like you said
你可以捷足先登
you could beat me in a climbing contest
当然可以了
'Course I can
我可是松鼠
I'm a squirrel
看吧
See
我还以为那标志表示你是坚果
I thought that meant you were nuts
不对
Nope
那标志表示我是天生攀岩好手
It means I'm a natural born climber
我是从陆地上来的
I'm from the surface world
想攀得一手好岩
and nothing prepares you for climbing
成长环境最好还得是干燥的陆地
like growing up on good old dry land
陆什么地
Land-shmand
手指力量才重要
It's all about finger strength, baby
在海底下最不缺的
And if there's anything we've got plenty of down here
就是手指力量
it's finger strength
怎么说呢  手套小姐
What do you say to that, Miss Mittens?
我已经到半山腰了
I say I'm already halfway there
不公平  珊迪
No fair, Sandy
你抢跑
You got a head start
抱歉  海绵宝宝
Sorry, SpongeBob
珊瑚就是这样一步步瓦解的
That's the way the coral crumbles
你是故意的
You did that on purpose
对  不过这次不是故意的
Yeah, but this is a accident
可惜你忘了带雨伞
Too bad you forgot your umbrella
我没忘
I didn't
你现在也该到了吧
Well, it's about time you showed up
可你刚
But you were
我看到你
I saw you
我
I
我要复赛
I want a rematch
谁第一个到蟹堡王谁就赢
First one to the Krusty Krab is the winner
海底生物绝对不可能
Ain't no way a sea critter
跑赢陆地生物
can run faster than a land critter
在水下绝对行
I can underwater
我
I'm
设计符合流体力学
hydrodynamically designed
穿着一身笨重的锡管还想赢
Think you can win a fair race in that clunky tin tube?
想问就先得落后我
Why don't you ask my be-hind?
也就是
That is
至少也得先赶上我
if you can catch it
你意下如何  流体动力宝宝
What do you say to that, Hydropants?
我都已经
I say, I'm already
到半路了
halfway there
谢谢你脸当我垫脚石
Thanks for the face lift
蟹堡王
早就跟你说你没
You see, I told you you didn't have a
终于到了
There you are
就是这位陆地生物
Ain't that just like a land creature
害一位海底生物
to keep a sea creature
苦等
waiting
你都说好了要复赛的
I thought y'all wanted a rematch
没错
I did
而且我跟你一样抢跑了
And I took a head start like you did
我那次只是在跟你开个玩笑
I was just funnin' with ya that time
不过看来你们海底生物
But I guess all y'all underwater
就是用不着公平竞争
don't have to play fair
确实  呼吸空气的
I guess we don't, air breather
吸水的
Water sucker
爬树的
Tree climber
住湾流的
Gulf streamer
放风筝的
Kite flier
吃鱼饵的
Chum chewer
收回你的话  你这个
Take that back, you
不湿的人
not-wet person
想不出别的外号了吧
You can't even come up with another name
证据确凿
That proves it
证什么了
Proves what?
陆地生物就是比海底生物强
That land critters are better than sea critters
强在哪了
Better at what?
大概是样样都强吧
Durn near everything, I guess
套牛  吃派
Cattle ropin and pie eatin'
还有砍树
and wood choppin'
还有飞行
and flyin'
她在唠叨什么
What's she blabbering about?
她说陆地生物最强
She says land creatures are best
因为本来就这样
Only 'cause it's true
我们最会骑马
We're best at horseridin'
还有理毛  赛艇
and fur stylin' and rowin'
虽说你们游泳比我强
Y'all got us licked in swimmin'
不过我们还会剥玉米
but we got corn shuckin'
铲干草  养畜禽
and hay bailin' and barn raisin'
还有钓鱼
and fishin'
当然还有人身攻击
And name callin' fer sure
还有溺水
And drowning
别忘了溺水
Don't forget drowning
真好笑  章鱼哥
Good one, Squidward
这辈子你都别想
Not on your life, sport
我承认
I'll admit
对于松鼠来说  你确实有点东西
You've got some pretty good moves, for a squirrel
但你还只是个陆地生物
But you're still just a land creature
松鼠想做什么就能做什么
Squirrels can do anything they want to
你肯定没法一口吃掉双层豪华蟹黄堡
I bet you can't eat a Krabby Double Deluxe in one bite
给我
Give me that
我奇克斯的名号可不是白叫的
They don't call me Cheeks for nothin'
大 脸 颊
区区一件小事
Well, that's just one thing
你能这样吗
Can you do this?
我家人全都会
Everyone in my family can do that
这个呢
How about this, huh?
你能出芽生殖吗
Can you reproduce by budding?
能吗
Can ya?
不能
No
最重要的是
Most importantly
你能这样吗
can you do this?
我干嘛要做那堆傻事
Well, what would I want to do
any of that dumb stuff for anyway?
承认吧  珊迪
Admit it, Sandy--
你做不了我们海底生物能做的事
you can't do anything us sea creatures can do
其实要不是你穿着那身衣服
In fact, if it wasn't for that suit
你都不能在这里活下来
you couldn't even live down here
你们都不
Well, you don't
我用不着
I don't need to
让你们见识
I'll show y'all
我用不着这套衣服
I don't need this suit
我也用不着这个头盔
And I don't need this helmet neither
海神王保佑她
Neptune preserve her
她能那样撑多久
How long can she stay like that?
不知道
I don't know
珊迪原来是女的
Sandy's a girl?
珊迪
Sandy
你确实证明我们错了
You sure proved us wrong
陆地生物确实更强
I guess land creatures are better
不过等憋不住要呼吸就弱下来了
At least, until they need to breathe
马上撑不下去了
Yep, won't be long now
头晕了没
Feeling lightheaded yet?
记得这个吗
Remember this?
免费的
It's free
腌椰菜
别笑我了
Stop laughin' at me
我就知道
I knew it
某些空气笨脑
There was no way some "airhead"
肯定赢不过在水里呼吸的
was going to win anything against a water breather
空气笨脑
Airhead
海底生物最强
Sea creatures rule
水
Water
好吧好吧
All right, all right
你们笑就笑吧
You had your little laugh
现在该我了
But now it's my turn
你们以为自己都是高手对吧
Y'all think you're such hot stuff, don't ya?
身上长了鳃就能四处游
Swimmin' around with your fancy gills 'n such
不过你们这群脑子进水的
But none of you wet heads
绝对在我的地盘撑不过一分钟
would last a minute on my turf
干燥陆地
Dry land
我们得戴腌椰菜瓶吗
Do we have to wear pickle jars?
你们只要穿自己的衣服上
Nope, nothin' but the clothes on your backs
才一分钟
One minute?
没问题
No problem
珊地
landy
你们还上不上了
Well, so are you going or not?
那个
Well
我们
we
其实
Actually
就是
you know
不能
We can't
因为
because
我们
We're
要赶不上
late for
试衣服了
Our fitting
该不会是要试穿胆小鸡皮套吧
You mean for your chicken costumes?
我们不是胆小鸡
We are not chicken
我的爆米花
My popcorn
对  我们不是胆小鸡
Yeah, we're not chicken
上就上
we'll do it
好了
There
任务完成
Mission accomplished
听好  要是不能在陆地待短短一分钟
Look, unless you can stay above water
for one measly minute
你们比赛就算是弃权
you forfeit the contest
并且证明陆地生物就是比海底生物强
and prove that land creatures
are better than sea creatures
想得美  珊迪
No way, San-day
我们接受你的挑战
We can take on your challenge
对
Yeah
我们不怕你的破陆地
We're not afraid of your dumb old land
对
Yeah
我们是海底生物
We're sea creatures
对
Yeah
好
Okay
就这样了
Well, this is it
等等  小子
Wait, boy
撑下去
Make it last
谢了  蟹老板
Thanks, Mr. Krabs
好
Okay
我要上了
Here I go
感觉还行
This isn't so bad
我们能行的
We can do this
派大星  快上来
Hey, Patrick, come on up
空气还行
The air is fine
我要速战速决
I'm gonna do it quick and get it over with
大炮来了
Cannonball
我裤子没了
I lost my trunks
嗨  海绵宝宝
Hi, SpongeBob
太好了  派大星
All right, Pat
你做到了
You made it
蟹老板
Mr. Krabs
快上来吧  蟹老板
Come on up, Mr. Krabs
到上面来
Up here
该上岸的都得上岸  章鱼哥先生
All ashore that's goin' ashore, Mr. Squidward
去陆地
Land
样子不错  蟹老板
Lookin' good, Mr. Krabs
好耶
Yeah
快来  章鱼哥
Come on, Squidward
干燥就快让你错过了
You're missing all the dry
快来  章鱼哥
Come on, Squidward
章鱼哥
Squidward
上就上
Well, I'll do it
然而我心不甘情不愿
but I won't like it
章鱼哥
Squidward
章鱼
Squid
怎么了
What?
我们到了
Well, here we are
还挺简单的
This is pretty easy
我可能要在这上面再整一颗石头住
I may keep a second rock up here
适应了陆地就能改善不少
Once you get your land legs, it's not so bad
我们是陆地和海洋的霸主
We're the masters of land and sea
是个土著
It's a local
嗨
Hi
我们是从海底来的
We're from underwater
你认识珊迪奇克斯吗
Do you know Sandy Cheeks?
三
Three
二
two
一
one
好家伙
Well, tan my fur
他们成功了
They made it
最好还是去祝贺他们
Better go congratulate them
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob?
派大星
Patrick?
他们都哪去了
Where did those critters get to?
我的天啊
Holy Guacamole
不许吃我朋友  长翅膀的耗子
You can't eat my friends, you rats with wings
谢谢你救了我们  珊迪
Thanks for saving us, Sandy
人人各有各的长处
You know everyone's best at something
但没人能样样精通
But no one's best at everything
抱歉之前让你摘掉头盔  珊迪
Sorry I made you take off your helmet, Sandy
抱歉之前让你上干燥的陆地  海绵宝宝
Sorry I made you go up on dry land, SpongeBob
为感到抱歉欢呼三声
Three cheers for feeling sorry for ourselves
一二
Hip-hip
万岁
Hooray
一二
Hip-hip
万岁
Hooray
一二
Hip-hip
万岁
Hooray
惹祸的花生
翻译: 1440kHz
导演
分镜总监
编剧
动画总监
创意总监
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
裤头村动物园             牡蛎体育场
年度免费节
啊
Ah
裤头村动物园
the Bikini Bottom Zoo
在举行年度免费节
is having its annual free day
免费气球
Free balloons
免费饮料
free drinks
免费灯泡
free light bulbs?
大家早上好啊
Top 'o the mornin', boys
下一站
Next stop
礼品店
gift shop
牡蛎体育场
我们到了
There it is--
牡蛎体育场
Oyster Stadium
那边不仅仅
Not only do they have
圈养着最大的牡蛎
the largest oyster held in captivity
还会演杂技
it also does tricks
牡蛎把大珍珠吐到了一百英尺高
He spits a giant pearl 100 feet in the air
宛如一颗炮弹
like a cannon ball
那我们还闲逛
Why are we hanging around
看你瞎模仿干什么
watching a cheap imitation?
直接过去看吧
Let's get over there
今天是我们一生中最棒的一天
This is the greatest day of our lives
今天是我们一生中最棒的一天吗
This is the greatest day of our lives?
无聊
Boring
你说得对  派大星
You're right, Patrick
我们要来看
we came to see
吐到一百英尺高的大珍珠
pearls 100 feet in the air
对吧
Right?
我来学牡蛎叫
I'll try my oyster call
我要走了
Well, I'm outta here
谢谢你带我白来一场  海绵宝宝
Thanks for nothin', SpongeBob
快啊快啊
Come on, come on
赶快醒过来
wake up already
海花生
好像成了
I think it's working
派大星  它醒过来了
Hey, Patrick, it's waking up
天啊  我错过了吗
Oh boy, did I miss it?
没  杂技才刚要开始演
No, the show's about to begin
大蚌
大蚌怎么了
What's wrong with Clamu?
小妹冷静
Easy, girl
是我小乔  还记得吗
it's me, Joe, remember?
这场杂技才好看
Now, this is a show
动物园游客请注意
Attention, zoo patrons
巨型牡蛎大蚌正在发狂
Clamu The Giant Oyster is on an emotional rampage
请尖叫并绕圈跑
Please scream and run around in circles
感谢大家光临
Thanks for coming
你们最好立刻离开
You boys better get out of this area, pronto
最危险的东西
There's nothing more dangerous
当属这只精神失常的大牡蛎
than an emotionally disturbed oyster
造成这场悲剧的应该不是你吧
You didn't do anything
that might have caused this tragedy, did you?
当然不是了
No way
只有大浑球才会害温和的大牡蛎生气
Only a jerk would upset a gentle giant
对吧  海绵宝宝
Right, SpongeBob?
对
Right
裤头村动物园
要是让我看到那位害大蚌生气的
Man, if I ever see the guy who upset Clamu
我有好几个备选的词来骂他  比如
I'd have a few choice words for him, like
你
"you"
还有
and
是
"are"
还有
and
混蛋
"a jerk"
确定没看到什么可疑的迹象吗
Are you sure you didn't see anything suspicious?
我都说没看到了  派大星
I already said I didn't, Patrick
来一起调查这场罪案
Let's investigate this crime
抓住作案的坏蛋
and catch the lowlife who's responsible
别闹了  派大星
Give it a rest, Patrick
根本就没罪案留给你查
There's no crime to investigate
给我回家
Now go home
笨蛋派大星
Stupid Patrick
我才没犯什么事
I didn't do anything wrong
还烦什么东西
What am I getting so worked up about?
等到明天
I'm sure that by tomorrow
这场大乱肯定会变成笑谈
this whole ugly mess will be a funny memory
今晚的头条新闻
Our top story tonight
巨型牡蛎遭受心理创伤
giant oyster has its feelings hurt
现场唯一的线索
The only clue that could be found
只有这一颗花生
was this lone peanut
大家可以听到
And as you can hear
牡蛎仍在凄惨地哭泣着
the oyster continues to emit its horrible cry
哭声之强  乃至全世界都能听到
A cry so powerful, it can be heard around the world
这哭声不但能打破音障
A cry that not only breaks the sound barrier
还伤了广大居民们的心
it breaks the hearts of our citizens
是怎样残暴淡漠又邪恶的人
What kind of cruel careless, evil person
会存心激怒海底最为温和的生物之一
would deliberately upset
one of Neptune's most gentle creatures?
才没  小蜗
No, Gary
我哪知道牡蛎的事
How would I know anything about the oyster?
狡辩
Defensive?
我才没狡辩
I'm not being defensive
真见鬼
Barnacles
什么鬼东西  问答游戏吗
What is this, 20 questions or something?
情况有点失控了
This is getting a little out of hand
我才扔了颗花生
All I did was throw a peanut
又没故意要惹哭牡蛎
I didn't mean to make the oyster cry
我只是想看它表演杂技
I just wanted to see it perform spectacular stunts
这下大家都要恨我了
Everyone's going to hate me
我  我需要建议
I, I need some advice
想想看
Now, let's see now
谁会不论我做了什么事都不恨我
who could never hate me no matter what I do?
章鱼哥
Squidward
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
你非得这么大声敲门吗
Do you have to knock so loudly?
抱歉  邻居
Sorry, neighbor
那头大蛤蜊
That overgrown clam
害我头疼死了
is giving me a headache
连午后美容觉都不让我睡好
I can't even take my afternoon beauty nap
你说到了那头老牡蛎  挺有趣的
Funny thing you should mention that old oyster
因为我
Because I
有点想知道
was kind wondering, um
我好像认得惹了牡蛎的那位
Let's say I know this guy
who may have something to do with the oyster
你认识犯事的那位
You know the guy who did it?
那可太好了
This is great
我和你能让他就地正法
You and I can go turn him in
然后我就能好好睡美容觉
And then I'll get so much sleep
再然后就帅起来了
I'll be gorgeous
其实我
Actually, I
我刚刚那是假设
I'm just talking hypothetically
你不认识真凶
You mean you don't know who did it?
那个
Well, um
我
I, uh
不认识
no
章鱼哥
Squidward
逮到你了
Gotcha
你今天的那天在哪里
Where were you on the day of today?
不许耍我  先生
Don't play games with me, mister
派大星  你在干什么
Hey, Patrick, what are you doing?
嗨  海绵宝宝
Hi, SpongeBob
我在继续大蚌案的调查
I'm just continuing my investigation
of the great Clamu Caper
有什么发现吗
Have you found out anything?
有
Yes
不对  等下
No, wait
没
no
不过这粒沙子感觉十分可疑
But this grain of sand looks pretty suspicious
这颗石头也是
and so does this rock
我还有几个问题想问这棵草
And I've got a few questions
for this little piece of grass
你放心  海绵宝宝
Don't worry, SpongeBob
派大星来破案
Patrick's on the case
真相要公诸于世
The truth will be revealed
去找珊迪  她知道该怎么办
I'd better go see Sandy, she'll know what to do
我再也受不了了
I can't stand it anymore
那个可怜的小家伙
That poor, poor critter
是怎样淡漠的人
What kind of inconsiderate person
居然会如此惹怒这样一只温和的生物
would upset such a gentle creature?
那就是我想跟你说的事  珊迪
That's kind of what I wanted to talk to you about, Sandy
等我找到严重伤害牡蛎的那位
Why, when I find out who caused that oyster so much pain
得让他再也耍不了大家
No more jiggery pokery
裤头村黄页
你刚刚想跟我说什么  海绵宝宝
Now, what was it you wanted to talk about, SpongeBob?
海绵宝宝  你怎么在抽搐
Hey, SpongeBob, how come you're all twitchy like that?
抽搐
Twitchy?
谁抽搐了
Who's twitchy?
我才没抽搐
I'm not twitchy
抱歉  珊迪
Sorry, Sandy
我得
I have to um
去剪头发
go get my hair cut
海绵宝宝没头发
SpongeBob doesn't have hair
不会还真有吧
or does he?
海绵宝宝
Hey, SpongeBob
我找到了
This is it
所有线索都汇聚在一起了
All of the clues are coming together
我跟着这些脚印到了这里
I followed these footprints right to this exact spot
然后  就是在你站的地方
and then, right where you're standing
我发现了这袋花生
I found this bag of peanuts
我就快侦破这起罪案了
I'm so close to solving this crime
都快尝得到了
I can almost taste it
天啊  打击犯罪让我饿坏了
Boy, crime-fighting sure makes me hungry
这根黄色冰棍刚好能解馋
and this yellow popsicle hits the spot
好吧
Okay, uh
祝你破案好运  派大星
good luck with all that, Patrick
然后
and, uh
等会见
I guess I'll see you later
开门
Open up
这里是警察
This is the police
先等一下
Just a second
你是海绵宝宝吗
Are you SpongeBob SquarePants?
什么事
Y-y-yes?
把眼球安回去
Put those eyeballs back in your head, son
我们有几个问题要问你
We've got a few questions for you
牡蛎事件发生那天  你在动物园吗
Were you at the zoo on the day of the oyster incident?
在
Yes
你是否参与了
Did you, or did you not take part
动物园的各项游乐活动
in various activities of zoo-time merriment?
是
Yes
你认得这颗花生吗
And are you familiar with this peanut?
物证A
对
Yes
还有一个问题
Just one more question
你是否先前在牡蛎窝
Is it true that you were at the oyster's lair
跟派大星先生在一起
with a Mr. Patrick Star?
对
Yes
是真的
It's true
全都是真的
It's all true
游乐活动
The merriment
花生
the peanut
派大星
the Patrick
我们想了解的就这些了
That's all we need to know, son
对他立案
Let's book him
你们也太强了
You guys are good
我最不会怀疑的人就是我自己
I'm the last person I would have suspected
可我一直都在找我自己
but I was looking for me all the time
好完美的犯罪
It's the perfect crime
对对
Yeah, yeah
跟法官说去吧  小粉红
tell it to the judge, pinky
不好
Oh no
派大星对监狱过敏
Patrick's too sensitive for the big house
警察
等等  停车
Wait, stop
我才是你们要抓的人
I'm the one you want
我才是罪犯
I am the criminal
牡蛎体育场
大家一起朝他扔花生
Hey, everybody, let's throw peanuts at him
看他会作何感想
and see how he likes it
都是我罪有应得
I get what I deserve
等等
Wait
先别扔花生
Hold your peanuts
派大星是无辜的
Patrick Star is innocent
我过来这里要揭露真相
I have come here to reveal the truth
人人都说只要诚实相待
They say that truth and honesty
方能换取信任与原谅
will be rewarded with trust and forgiveness
我在此向大家坦白
I'm here to lay my cards on the table
以此砍去我生命之树上的欺瞒枝杈
to trim the branches of deception from the tree of life
刮去我真相之脸上的邋遢鬓角
to shave away the unkempt sideburns
from the face of truth
我
I
有话快说
Just get on with it
是我扔的花生
I am the one who threw the peanut
现在我明白我的所作所为铸成了大错
I know now that what I have done is wrong
我要向大家说
and so I say
对不起  巨型杂技牡蛎
I am sorry, giant performing oyster
对不起  派大星
I am sorry, Patrick
对不起  裤头村居民们
I am sorry, citizens of Bikini Bottom
大家朝他们两个扔花生
Let's throw peanuts at both of 'em
等等
Wait
这才是真正的罪犯
Here's the real criminal
早上好
Top of the morning
蟹老板
Mr. Krabs
我就知道
I knew it
蟹老板偷了牡蛎一样非常重要的东西
Mr. Krabs has stolen a very important item
from the oyster
大家看
Behold
等一下
Wait a minute
大家看
Behold
牡蛎的珍珠
The oyster's pearl
还给你  小妹
Here you go, girl
妈妈
Mama
珍珍的妈啊
Mother of pearl
那只牡蛎是位母亲
The oyster's a mother
而且珍珠也不是珍珠
And that pearl's no pearl
而是颗卵
It's an egg
妈妈
Mama
可今天是免费节
But it's free day